A Guide to the Papers of U.S. Congressman L.F. Payne, Jr. 1987-1996
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of U.S. Congressman L.F. Payne, Jr. 1987-1996
11270
This collection consists of the congressional papers of Representative L.F. Payne, Jr., 1987-1996, ca. 6,700 items (12 Hollinger boxes, ca. 5 linear shelf feet).
This collection consists of the congressional papers of Representative L.F. Payne, Jr., 1987-1996, ca. 6,700 items pertaining to Payne's career from the 5th District of Virginia, including press releases; newsletters; committee and subcommittee reports, documents, reports, memoranda, minutes, correspondence, and transcripts of testimony from hearings.Also present in the collection are subject files on topics such as the North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA); General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT); regional air & water quality and other environmental issues; issues related to businesses in Virginia, such as Babcock and Wilcox, Multitrade Limited Partnership, the impact of the Federal Prison Industries upon Virginia furniture makers, and the possibility of having a Martinsville Manufacturing Technology Center; airports in Virginia; Housing Conferences and the Low Income Housing Tax Credit; and issues affecting Virginia's parks and natural areas, such as the Shenandoah National Park & Skyline Drive, the Wilderness areas, Appalachian Trail, and the Kerr Reservoir. Files pertaining to Thomas Jefferson include those concerning "Poplar Forest", the 250th celebration of his birth, and a special commemorative coin. Topics related to Charlottesville and Albemarle County include the Albemarle Housing Improvement Program (AHIP), the Wiseman House Project, and Sperry Marine.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
L.F. Payne, Jr. of Wintergreen, Virginia, gave these papers to the University of Virginia Library on December 18, 1996.
Biographical/Historical Information
Prior to 1992, L.F. Payne served on the House of Representatives Public Works and Transportation Committee and the House Budget Committee. In 1992, Payne was appointed to the Ways & Means Committee. Bills introduced into the 103rd Congress by L.F. Payne include: H.R. 5070, H.R. 3106, H.R. 2759, H.R. 2383, H.R. 2384, H.R. 2385, H.R. 2031, H.R. 1939, H.R. 997, H.R. 860, and H.R. 789.
Lewis Franklin Payne, Jr., was born in Amherst County, Virginia, on July 9, 1945, and attended the Amherst County public schools. Payne received his B.S. degree in Civil Engineering from the Virginia Military Institute in 1967, and his M.B.A. from the University of Virginia Darden School of Business in 1973, after serving as a company commander in the United States Army Corps of Engineers, 1968-1970, and three years in the U.S. Army Reserves. He worked as a staff engineering associate with the C & P Telephone Company, 1970-1971; and a planning and development manager of Wintergreen Development Company, Inc., Wintergreen, Virginia, (1973- 1975); later serving as president (1976-1985) and chairman of the board (1985-1988).
Payne is also on the Board of Directors of the Patrick Henry Boys Foundation, a member of the American Legion Post 16 in Lynchburg, and a trustee of the Rockfish Presbyterian Church in Nellysford, Virginia. As president of the Nelson County Community Development Foundation, Payne developed Montreal Village in Nelson County, Virginia, to promote homes for low and middle income families. Montreal Village won the Department of Housing and Urban Development Certification of National Merit in 1989.
Payne was elected as a Democrat to the 100th Congress, June 14, 1988, by special election to fill the vacancy caused by the death of Wilbur Clarence (Dan) Daniel and served from 1988 to 1996, when he resigned to run in the election for Lt. Governor of Virginia. From 1990-1992, Payne served on the Veteran's Affairs Committee and the House Public Works and Transportation Committee where he was instrumental in achieving reforms to the federal highway funding formulas that increased Virginia's allocation of highway funds.
During the 102nd Congress, he served on the House Budget Committee, as a leading proponent of the Balanced Budget Amendment to the U.S. Constitution, the line-item veto, and a seven year balanced budget plan developed in 1995 by the "Coalition," a group of moderate-to-conservative House Democrats that Payne helped establish in the 104th Congress, whose members are known as "Blue Dog Democrats." From 1993 until 1996, Payne was a member of the House Ways and Means Committee, serving on its Social Security and Trade subcommittees. L.F. Payne is married to Susan King and they have four children, Graham, Hunter, Sara, and Anna Payne.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of the congressional papers of Representative L.F. Payne, Jr., 1987-1996, ca. 4,500 items pertaining to Payne's career from the 5th District of Virginia, including press releases; newsletters; committee and subcommittee reports, documents, reports, memoranda, minutes, correspondence, and transcripts of testimony from hearings.
Organization
The collection is divided into two series: I. Columns and Press Releases and II. Legislative Files.
Contents List
- COLUMNS & PRESS RELEASES (Box 1-2)
  - Columns 1988-1996, 8 folders (Box 1)
  - Press Releases 1988, 1991-1996, 4 folders (Box 2)
- LEGISLATIVE FILES (Box 2-12)
  Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Airport Projects in the 5th District 1991-1995 (Box 2)
  - Albermarle Housing Improvement Program (AHIP) 1993-1994 (Box 2)
  - Appalachian Trail 1991 (Box 2)
  - Babcock and Wilcox - Highly Enriched Uranium (HEU) & Russian Deal 1994 (Box 2)
    includes a letter from Bill Clinton
  - Babcock and Wilcox - Hot Cell Amendment to Energy Bill 1990-1992, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Babcock and Wilcox - Nuclear Weapons Complex 1991-1992 (Box 3)
  - Bills Introduced by L.F. Payne during the 103rd Congress 1993-1994 (Box 3)
  - Budget 1995-1996 (Box 3)
  - Chief Financial Officers Act of 1990 1991-1994 (Box 3)
  - Clean Water Act - Combined Sewer Overflow Construction - Lynchburg 1993-1996 (Box 3)
  - Clean Water Act - Combined Sewer Overflow Construction - Richmond 1989-1995 (Box 3)
  - Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands "Saipan Bill" 1992-1993, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Co-signed Letters 1991-1994 (Box 4)
  - Environmental Protection Agency - Interagency Work Group for Air Quality Modeling (IWAQM) 1991-1993 (Box 4)
  - Environmental Protection Agency - Martinsville Permit 1995 (Box 4)
  - Environmental Protection Agency - Multitrade Limited Partnership facility (PSD) Prevention of Significant Deterioration Permit 1990-1994, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Environmental Protection Agency - Regional Air Quality Commission 1991-1994 (Box 4)
  - Environmental Protection Agency - Water Quality Standards - 5th District Problems 1992-1994 (Box 4)
  - Essential Air Services Program 1993-1995 (Box 4)
  - Export Conference Backround 1992-1994, 2 folders and a bound volume Breaking Into the Trade Game (Box 4)
  - Federal Aviation Administration's Contract Tower Program 1994 (Box 5)
  - Federal Prison Industries (FPI) 1991-1996, 2 folders and a bound set of documents presented to the House Small Business Committee by the Quarters Furniture Manufacturers Association and the Business & Institution Furniture Manufacturers Association (Box 5)
  - General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT) - Uruguay Round - American Textile Manufacturer's Institute (ATMI) Legislative Language 1994 (Box 5)
  - General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT) - Uruguay Round - Anti-dumping 1994 Apr 29 (Box 5)
  - General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT) - Uruguay Round - Anti-dumping Proposals 1994 Jul 15 (Box 5)
  - General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT) - Uruguay Round - Anti-dumping (Executive Session) 1994 Jun 16 (Box 5)
  - General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT) - Caribbean Basin Initiative Parity Amendment 1994 Jul 20 (Box 5)
  - General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT) - Uruguay Round - Conference 1994, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT) - Uruguay Round - Factual Background & Charter 1990-1994 (Box 6)
  - General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT) - Uruguay Round - Financial Services Negotiations 1993 (Box 6)
  - General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT) - Uruguay Round - Financing Provisions 1994 (Box 6)
  - General Afreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT) - Uruguay Round - Hearing (Full committee) with Ambassador Michael Kantor 1994 Jan 26 (Box 6)
  - General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT) - Uruguay Round - Hearing (Subcommittee) 1993 Nov 4 (Box 6)
  - General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT) - Uruguay Round - Hearing (Subcommittee) 1993 Nov 5 (Box 6)
  - General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT) - Uruguay Round - Hearing (Subcommittee) 1994 Feb 1 (Box 6)
  - General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT) - Uruguay Round - Hearing (subcommittee) 1994 Feb 2 (Box 6)
  - General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT) - Uruguay Round - Hearing (Subcommittee) 1994 Feb 8 (Box 7)
  - General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT) Uruguay Round - Hearing (Subcommittee) 1994 Feb 22 (Box 7)
  - General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT) - Uruguay Round -H.R. 4066 International Games Duty Suspension- Executive Session (Full Committee) 1994 Mar 23 (Box 7)
  - General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT) - Uruguay Round - Mark up Documents 1994 May 16 (Box 7)
  - General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT) - Uruguay Round - Mark up Documents 1994 May 26 (Box 7)
  - General agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT) - Uruguay Round - Mark up Documents 1994 Jun 20 (Box 7)
  - General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT) - Uruguay Round -Mark up Documents 1994 Jul 20 (Box 7)
  - General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT) - Uruguay Round - Mark up Documents - Amendments 1994 Jun 29 (Box 7)
  - General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT) - Uruguay Round - Publicity, "Dear Colleague" Letters and Letters from Constituents in the 5th District 1994 (Box 8)
  - General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT) - Uruguay Round - Section 301 and W.T.O. Dispute Settlement/Fast Track - Executive Session (Subcommittee) 1994 Mar 3 (Box 8)
  - General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT) - Uruguay Round - Textile Background 1993-1994 (Box 8)
  - General Agreement on Tariffs and Tarde (GATT) - Uruguay Round - Textile Impact - Cardin-Breaux Rule of Origin Amendment 1994 (Box 8)
  - General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT) - Uruguay Round - Trade Agreements Draft Implementing Proposal 1994 May-Jul, 3 folders (Box 8)
  - General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT) - Uruguay Round - Trans-shipment & Importer Information 1994 (Box 8)
  - General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT) - Uruguay Round - World Trade Organization (WTO) Hearing 1994 Jun 10 (Box 8)
  - Housing Conferences at Longwood College, Farmville, Virginia, dedicated to affordable housing in Virginia 1990-1996, 3 folders (Box 9)
  - John H. Kerr Reservoir, Halifax County 1992-1994 (Box 9)
  - John H. Kerr Reservoir, Halifax County - Mosquito Control 1991-1994 (Box 9)
  - Low Income Housing Tax Credit/Budget Reconciliation Conference 1995-1996 (Box 9)
  - Low Income Housing Tax Credit/Mortgage Revenue Bond (H.R. 18) 1993-1994 (Box 9)
  - Manufactured Home Construction and Safety Standards 1993-1995 (Box 9)
  - Martinsville Manfuacturing Technology Center 1992-1993 May, 1 of 3 folders (Box 9)
  - Martinsville Manufacturing Technology Center 1993 Sep-Dec, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous 1989,1995 (Box 10)
  - North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) - "Carribbean Basin Free Trade Agreements Act" H.R. 1403 Hearing 1993 Jun 24 (Box 10)
  - North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) - "Caribbean Basin Free Trade Agreements Act" H.R. 1403 Hearing (Background Material) 1993 Mar-Jun (Box 10)
  - North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) - Caribbean Basin Initiative (CBI), Parity with NAFTA 1994 (Box 10)
  - North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) - Caribbean Basin Initiative (CBI), Parity with NAFTA - Graham Proposal 1993 Oct (Box 10)
  - "North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) and the Fifth District - Two Years Later" ca. 1995-1996 (Box 10)
  - North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) - Hearing 1993 Sep 21 (Box 10)
  - North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) - Hearing (Full Committee) 1993 Sep 14 (Box 11)
  - North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) - Hearing (Subcommittee) 1993 Sep 15 (Box 11)
  - North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) - Hearing (Subcommittee) 1993 Sep 23 (Box 11)
  - North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) - Hearing Supplementals 1993 (Box 11)
  - North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) - Markup Documents (Full Committee) 1993 Oct 5 (Box 11)
  - North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) - Markup Documents (Full Committee) 1993 Nov 9 (Box 11)
  - North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) - Markup Documents (Full Committee) - Customs Modernization Act 1993 Oct 21 (Box 11)
  - North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) - Markup Documents (Full Committee) - Funding 1993 Oct 27 (Box 11)
  - North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) - Markup Documents (Full Committee) - Medical Professionals 1993 Nov 9 (Box 11)
  - North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) - Markup Documents (Full Committee) - Member Amendments 1993 Sep-Oct (Box 11)
  - North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) - Markup Documents (Full Committee) - Payne Amendment 1993 Oct 8-21 (Box 11)
  - North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) - Markup Documents (Full Committee) - Statement of Administrative Action 1993 Oct 12 & 19 (Box 11)
  - North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) - Markup Documents (Full Committee) - Worker Adjustment 1993 (Box 11)
  - North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) - Markup Documents (Full Committee) - Worker Retraining ca. 1993 (Box 11)
  - North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) - Markup Documents (Trade Subcommittee) 1993 Sep 30 (Box 11)
  - "Poplar Forest," Bedford County ,Virginia 1992-1993 (Box 12)
  - Powhatan Arrow Railcar from Saudi Arabia 1987,1991-1992 (Box 12)
  - Resource Conservation and Recovery Act (Subtitle D Regulations) 1991-1994 (Box 12)
  - Route 58 Corridor Development Program 1994-1995 (Box 12)
  - Rubatex Tariff Bill (H.R. 5183) 1992 (Box 12)
  - Shenandoah National Park & Skyline Drive 1992-1993 (Box 12)
  - Sperry Marine 1993-1994 (Box 12)
  - Taxation of Farm Bureau Associate Member Dues (H.R. 3951) 1994-1995 (Box 12)
  - Thomas Jefferson Coin 1993 (Box 12)
  - Thomas Jefferson Commemoration Commission Act 1992-1995 (Box 12)
  - Thomas Jefferson Study to Preserve and Assess the Regional Environment (SPARE) 1993 (Box 12)
  - Veteran's Issues 1992 (Box 12)
  - Virginia Wilderness Areas 1991-1992 (Box 12)
  - White House Conference on Environmental Technology 1994 & 1996 (Box 12)
  - Wiseman House Project, Charlottesville, Virginia, for AIDS patients 1994 (Box 12)